Finding Aid for Canterbury House, Ann Arbor, Mich. records, 1930-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Canterbury House, Ann Arbor, Mich. records 1930-2008
Canterbury House (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
1 oversize folders
5 linear feet
0648 Ba 2; Ba Out
Episcopal student chaplaincy established in 1945 as the Episcopal Student Foundation to minister to University of Michigan students. The activities of the ministry were centered in Canterbury House (various locations). The Canterbury House ministry functioned both as a coffee house and as a performance hall for folk and jazz artists. The record group divides into three series. History and background materials include histories, promotional materials, and newspaper articles. The Episcopal Student Foundation Board of Trustees series consists of minutes, financial records, correspondence, and files relating to building facilities. The Canterbury series documents non-administrative activities, including staffing, chaplain activities, and programs and performances sponsored. This series also includes photographs, sound recordings, and files relating to the Institute of Public Theology and the conferences sponsored by it.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records came from Canterbury House Episcopal Campus Ministry (donor no. 9670 ) on November 22, 2005. Additional materials were received in June 2006.
The record group is open to research.
Bishop Samuel Harris first proposed the idea for an Episcopal Student Church at the University of Michigan in 1885. This led to the building of Harris Hall, the creation of the Hobart Guild to manage the hall, and a series of Episcopal lectureships in Ann Arbor. Until 1935, the parish of St. Andrew's, the nearest Episcopal Church, oversaw the activities of the Hobart Guild and the Hall. In 1935, the Church began to employ a full time Counselor for Women's Students and in 1939, it employed a full time Chaplain. After the war, members of the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan, St. Andrew's Church and other lay members and clergy formed the Episcopal Student Foundation. This formation created a formal and separate vehicle for Episcopal student work at the University of Michigan. In the summer of 1946, the board hired its first full time Chaplain. In 1947, the Board bought a property at 218 North Division Street, directly across the street from St. Andrew's Church. This house became known as Canterbury House and Episcopal student ministry continued through the 1960s. In 1953, the ESF Board was given ownership of a portfolio of stocks called the Church-Nichols Trust. The presence of this Trust gave the Board a much larger and secure budget.
In 1967, Canterbury made the move to an old print shop on Maynard in downtown Ann Arbor. There it functioned as a campus ministry and coffee house during the day and converted to a concert hall on the weekends, attracting a great deal of attention and big-name performers like Odetta, Joni Mitchell, Neil Young, and Gordon Lightfoot. The ministry represented a convergence of the turmoil of the time and the role of the traditional Church. After 1971, Canterbury moved back to 218 North Division and a more subdued ministry. In the 1970s, the ministry took an interest in the growing Gay and Lesbian movement and was the site for homosexual support groups. In 1978, hoping to invigorate the student body and the ministry as they had in the 60s, the House moved to a location on South State Street and became Canterbury Loft. Though the Loft was the site of a number of presentations and performances, it did not garner the same level of publicity and social effect as had the Coffee House. In 1984, Canterbury once again moved back to their old location across from St. Andrew's and was again called Canterbury House.
The chaplaincy of Virginia Peacock beginning in 1987 represented another big change for the house. As a female chaplain, Peacock took a special interest in women's issues, especially the role of women in the church. Peacock was also herself a PhD and was interested in bringing more academia to the House. In the 1990s, she helped found the Institute of Public Theology. When the Reverend Matthew Lawrence replaced Peacock in 1996, he took over the Institute and organized a number of events. The element that Lawrence helped invigorate was music coupled with worship. He began inviting musicians to accompany masses that eventually led to a highly successful Jazz Mass. However, during his tenure and especially after he left, the Institute seems to have faded from view. The focus of the Canterbury House since the departure of Chaplain Lawrence has been on sustaining the Jazz Mass and increasingly on fundraising. When choosing a new Chaplain in 2003, the main focus was on obtaining a chaplain skilled in fundraising.
The Canterbury House records contain the records of the Episcopal Student Foundation and the Canterbury House, the Episcopal Campus Church at the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor, Michigan. The records are divided into four series, History and Background Materials, Episcopal Student Foundation Board of Trustees, Staff, and Canterbury.
Subjects:
Canterbury House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Church history.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Episcopal Student Foundation.; Institute of Public Theology.; University of Michigan--Students--Religious life.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Canterbury House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Coffee houses--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Students--Religious life.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Canterbury House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan--Students--Religious life.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- History and Background Material circa 1930-2005
  The History and Background Materials series (0.3 linear feet) contains documents telling the history of Canterbury House, promotional materials, and newspaper articles dating from the 1930s to 2005.
  - Histories of Canterbury House (Box 1)
  - Duties of the Chaplain at Canterbury House (Box 1)
  - Promotional Materials 1950-2005 (Box 1)
    (also in oversize folder)
  - Newspaper Articles 1930-2005 (Box 1)
- Episcopal Student Foundation Board of Trustees 1945-2005
  The Episcopal Student Foundation Board of Trustees (ESF Board) series, (1.7 linear feet) covers the administrative business of the Canterbury House and contains five sub-series. The Foundational sub-series contains the mission statement, by-laws, and state documents for the ESF Board. Board Meetings contains lists of board members, agendas, minutes, reports, and all other documents associated with meetings of the ESF Board arranged by fiscal year from 1945 until 2005. Financial documents are arranged by the traditional fiscal year until the end of 1992 when the ESF discovered a canon in the Episcopal Church dictating that the fiscal year was to be the calendar year. After that point, documents are arranged by calendar year. Correspondence is organized alphabetically by subject, when applicable, and correspondent. Finally, the Buildings sub-series contains folders organized chronologically by property of the real estate and buildings owned by the ESF Board and Canterbury House.
  - Foundational
    - Mission Statement (Box 1)
    - By-Laws (Box 1)
    - State Documents (Box 1)
  - Board Meetings
    - July 1945-June 2005 (Box 1)
      (9 folders)
    - Lutheran-Episcopal Partnership 1991-1994 (Box 1)
  - Financial
    - July 1946-June 2004 (Box 1)
      (3 folders)
    - Church-Nichols Trust Founding 1953 (Box 2)
    - Church-Nichols Trust Correspondence 1953-1967, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Coffee House Fundraising 1966-1971 (Box 2)
    - South African Divestment 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - Requests to Special Ministries Committee 1980-1985 (Box 2)
    - General Correspondence 1957-1998 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - Board Members 1961-1996 (Box 2)
    - Danforth Foundation 1968 (Box 2)
    - Chaplain Foster 1974-1984 (Box 2)
    - Chaplain Lawrence 1997-1999 (Box 2)
    - Chaplain Peacock 1987-1996 (Box 2)
    - Chaplain Taylor 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Tim Wittlinger 1990-1997 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Buildings
    - 617 East Huron Property (Harris Hall) 1960-1966 (Box 2)
    - 506 Maple Ridge Property 1962-1963 (Box 2)
    - 330 Maynard Property (Coffee House) 1966 (Box 2)
    - 218 North Division Property 1966-1970 (Box 2)
    - 332 South State Property (Canterbury Loft) 1978 (Box 2)
    - Moving Plans 1984 (Box 2)
    - 721 East Huron Property 1995-circa 2003 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Properties 1962-1966 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Staff 1959-2004
  The Staff series contains three sub-series. Correspondence contains letters to and from Canterbury House chaplains and staff from 1959 to 1999. Chaplain Selection contains four folders covering part of the selection process for a new Chaplains from 1962 to 1996. Finally, Chaplain Activities is organized by chaplain, covering Chaplain and Canterbury House relations with other institutions, the University of Michigan community, the public at large, and the worship activities of the chaplains.
  - Correspondence
    - Chaplain Edward Roth 1959-1961 (Box 2)
    - Chaplain Lester Dobyns 1962-1963 (Box 2)
    - Associate Chaplain Robert Hauert 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - Chaplain Daniel Burke 1969 (Box 2)
    - Chaplain Andrew Foster 1983-1985 (Box 2)
    - Interim Chaplain Jim Taylor 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Chaplain Virginia Peacock 1987-1996 (Box 2)
    - Chaplain Matthew Lawrence 1996-1999 (Box 2)
    - Staff 1963-1993 (Box 2)
  - Chaplain Selection
    - Lester Dobyns 1962 (Box 2)
    - Craig Hammond 1967 (Box 2)
    - Virginia Peacock 1987 (Box 2)
    - Matthew Lawrence 1996 (Box 2)
  - Chaplain Activities
    - Andrew Foster
      - Calendar September 1973-December 1974 (Box 2)
      - Province V Conference Activities 1977-1985 (Box 2)
      - Association of Religious Counselors 1983-1986 (Box 2)
      - Study of Campus Ministries undated (Box 2)
    - Virginia Peacock
      - Diocese of Michigan 1987-1996 (Box 2)
      - Newsletters 1987-1996 (Box 2)
      - Mailings to Faculty and Staff 1987-1996 (Box 2)
      - UM Involvement 1987-1996 (Box 2)
      - Collaborative Work 1987-1996 (Box 2)
      - Sermons 1993-1994 (Box 2)
      - Women's Liturgy 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - Matthew Lawrence
      - Newsletters 1997-2001 (Box 3)
      - Homelessness Activism 1996-1997 (Box 3)
      - Publications 1999, 2001 (Box 3)
      - Sermons 1997 (Box 3)
      - Liturgical Principles 1999 (Box 3)
    - D. Rebecca Deinsen 2003 (Box 3)
    - Reid Hamilton
      - Newsletters 2006-2008 (Box 3)
      - Editorial 2004 (Box 3)
    - School of Social Work Internship, Mary Mengel 1992 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous 1974-2004 (Box 3)
  - Programs
    - Coffee House 1966-1971
      - General (Box 3)
      - Performers
        - 6th Street Theater (Box 3)
        - David Ackles (Box 3)
        - Luther Allison (Box 3)
        - The Botolph Group (Box 3)
        - Tim Buckley (Box 3)
        - Buddy Guy Blues Band (Box 3)
        - The Byrds (Box 3)
        - Guy Carawan (Box 3)
        - Carnal Kitchen (Box 3)
        - Len Chandler (Box 3)
        - Michael Cooney (Box 3)
        - Jack Elliot (Box 3)
- Canterbury
  The Canterbury series (3 linear feet) contains the non-administrative activities of the Canterbury House organization. This series includes five sub-series, Programs, Institute of Public Theology, Topical Files, Photographs, and Sound Recordings. The Programs sub-series contains the records of the famous Coffee House that Canterbury ran from 1966 to 1971. The records of the performers are arranged alphabetically by artist. After 1971, the records are arranged by event. These records show the types of programs held at Canterbury throughout the years in an effort to reach out to University students. The Institute of Public Theology sub-series represents the work of Canterbury House in bringing a dialog about the meaning of religion in 1990s. This sub-series contains the founding and sustaining documents of the Institute and the programs sponsored by the Institute. Topical Files contains 6 folders of material gathered by Canterbury House for their own research. Photographs are arranged chronologically by subject. Finally, the Sound Recordings sub-series contains 33 reel-to-reel tapes from 1964 to 1972. These tapes include recorded performances at the Coffee House, musical religious services, and other religious services.
  - Programs
    - Coffee House 1966-1971
      - Performers
        - Steve Elliot (Box 3)
        - John Fahey (Box 3)
        - Jesse Fuller (Box 3)
        - Good News (Box 3)
        - Odetta Gordon (Box 3)
        - John Hammond (Box 3)
        - Janis Ian (Box 3)
        - James Cotton Blues Band (Box 3)
        - Jim and Jean (Box 3)
        - Jim Kweskin Jug Band (Box 3)
        - Janis Joplin (Box 3)
        - "Spider" John Koerner and Willie Murphy (Box 3)
        - Gordon Lightfoot (Box 3)
        - Little Feat (Box 3)
        - Joni Mitchell (Box 3)
        - The New Lost City Ramblers (Box 3)
        - Penny Nichols (Box 3)
        - Steve Noonan (Box 3)
        - Paul Phillips (Box 3)
        - Radical Theater Reparatory (Box 3)
        - David Rea (Box 3)
        - Judy Roderick (Box 3)
        - Tom Rush (Box 3)
        - San Francisco Mime Troupe (Box 3)
        - Skip James (Box 3)
        - Mike Seeger (Box 3)
        - Sorry Muthas (Box 3)
        - The Spike Drivers (Box 3)
        - Mark Spoelstra (Box 3)
        - Jeremy Steig and the Satyrs (Box 3)
        - Roosevelt Sykes (Box 3)
        - The Times Square Two (Box 3)
        - Dave Van Ronk (Box 3)
        - Doc Watson (Box 3)
        - Neil Young (Box 3)
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Publicity (Box 3)
      - Event Booking, Fall 1970 (Box 3)
      - Services (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Register of Church Services November 6, 1966-September 1, 1975 (Box 3)
    - All Saints Day November 1, 1970 (Box 3)
    - David Tracy Lecture 1991 (Box 3)
    - Miserable Offenders 1995 (Box 3)
    - Parker Palmer Lecture 1998 (Box 3)
    - Liturgy and Sacred Music Project Grant 1999 (Box 3)
    - Jazz Mass 1999-2003 (Box 3)
    - Meet the Composer Grant 2003-2004 (Box 3)
    - From Narnia With Love 2003, 2004 (Box 3)
    - General
      - July 1975-June 2005 (Box 4)
        (6 folders)
      - Undated (Box 4)
  - Institute of Public Theology
    - Founding and Sustaining Documents 1992-1996 (Box 4)
    - Purpose and Goals 1992-1996 (Box 4)
    - Jonathan Edwards Conference 1993 (Box 4)
    - Jonathan Edwards Conference Papers
      (2 folders)
      - Bearce, Jeff (Box 4)
      - Bensick, Carol M. (Box 4)
      - Cernich, Chris (Box 4)
      - Chironna, Paul (Box 4)
      - Conkin, Paul (Box 4)
      - Daniel, Stephen H. (Box 4)
      - Ellingsen, Mark (Box 4)
      - Hoopes, Jim (Box 4)
      - Laskowsky, Henry J. (Box 4)
      - Lowance, Mason (Box 4)
      - Marini, Stephen A. (Box 4)
      - McCoy, Genevieve (Box 4)
      - McDermott, Gerald (Box 4)
      - Peacock, Virginia (Box 4)
      - Pierce, C. S. (Box 4)
      - Ryder, John (Box 4)
      - Spohn, William (Box 4)
      - Storlie, Erik F. (Box 4)
      - Stuart, Bruce W. (Box 4)
      - Taylor, John A. (Box 4)
      - Wainwright, William (Box 4)
    - Value Seminars 1993-1994 (Box 4)
    - Conflict & Community Seminars 1994-1995 (Box 4)
    - Trinity Institute Downlink: Jesus at 2000 1996 (Box 4)
  - Topical Files
    - Changing Campus Ministry 1968 (Box 4)
    - Ethics (Box 4)
    - Feminism (Box 4)
    - Sex (Box 4)
    - Sexuality (Box 4)
    - Weapons, Kellerman Research (Box 4)
  - Photographs, circa 1950s-1990s
    - Coffee House 1967-1971
      - Performances (Box 4)
      - Audiences (Box 4)
      - Artists Publicity (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - 721 East Huron Property 1997 (Box 4)
    - Jazz Mass undated (Box 4)
    - House Gatherings circa 1950s-1960s, 1990s (Box 4)
    - Winter Retreats undated (Box 4)
    - Chaplains Lawrence and Peacock undated (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous undated (Box 4)
  - Sound recordings
    (all 7 in. reel-to-reel; 7 1/2 ips except where noted)
    - Performances
      - The Fantasticks February, 1964 (Box 5)
        (tape nos. 1-2)
      - Coffee House 1966-1971
        - David Ackles (Box 5)
          (tape no. 12)
        - Guy Carawan (Box 5)
          (tape no. 21)
        - Len Chandler / Jon Miller (Box 5)
          (tape no. 7)
        - Al Finney (Box 5)
          (tape no. 17)
        - Music of Bob Franke including Celebrant by Craig Hammond and Parables read by Chaplain Dan Burke (Box 5)
          (tape no. 9)
        - Good News (Box 5)
          (tape no. 14)
        - Jim Kweskin Jug Band (Box 5)
          (tape no. 3)
        - Jim Kweskin, 5 in. reel to reel (Box 5)
          (tape no. 13)
        - "Spider" John Koerner (Box 5)
          (tape no. 8)
        - Steve Noonan (Box 5)
          (tape no. 11)
        - Odetta (Box 5)
          (tape no. 6)
        - Paul Phillips (Box 5)
          (tape no. 4)
        - David Rea (Box 5)
          (tape no. 10)
        - Ed and Pat Reynolds (Box 5)
          (tape no. 16)
        - Judy Roderick (Box 5)
          (tape no. 5)
        - Mark Spoelstra (Box 5)
          (tapes nos. 18-20)
        - David Von Ronk, 3 3/4 ips (Box 5)
          (tape no. 15)
    - Services
      - Communion Services March 10, 1968, March 24, 1968 (Box 5)
        (tape no. 22)
      - Service at Canterbury House, Commander Cody & LPA (Huron Valley Gospel Aires) October 27, 1968 (Box 5)
        (tape no. 23)
      - Service at Canterbury House January 19, 1969, 5 in. reel to reel) (Box 5)
        (tape no. 24)
      - Tape for Movement Mass April 5, 1970 (Box 5)
        (tape no. 25)
      - Andrew [Foster]'s Ordination February 21, 1971 (Box 5)
        (tape no. 26)
      - Spirit Retreat October 16, 1971 (Box 5)
        (tape no. 27)
      - Christmas Eve, The Alley December 24, 1971 (Box 5)
        (tape no. 28)
      - Christmas Eve Service, C. Hammond undated (Box 5)
        (tape no. 29)
      - Liturgical Workshop Tape March 4, 1972 (Box 5)
        (tape no. 30)
    - Miscellaneous Tapes
      - WCBN 11th Hour September 11, 1968 (Box 5)
        (tapes nos. 31-32)
      - Canterbury House Tape, Outcue "Words by Pete Seeger," undated (Box 5)
        (tape no. 33)